<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A sermon preached before the King at Chester, on August xxviii, 1687, being the feast of S. Augustin, Doctor of the Holy Catholic Church by ... Lewis Sabran ...</title>
            <author>Sabran, Lewis, 1652-1732.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1687</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 82 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 18 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A58905</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing S221</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R1786</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">13173426</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 13173426</idno>
            <idno type="VID">98331</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A58905)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 98331)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 777:15)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A sermon preached before the King at Chester, on August xxviii, 1687, being the feast of S. Augustin, Doctor of the Holy Catholic Church by ... Lewis Sabran ...</title>
                  <author>Sabran, Lewis, 1652-1732.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 33 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Henry Hills,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1687.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Marginal notes.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  N.T. --  Timothy, 2nd, IV, 7 --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-03</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-03</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:98331:1"/>
            <p>A SERMON Preached before the KING AT CHESTER, ON AUGUST xxviii. 1687.</p>
            <p>Being the FEAST of S. AUGUSTIN, Doctor of the Holy <hi>Catholic Church.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By the Reverend Father, LEWIS SABRAN, of the Society of Jeſus.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Publiſhed by His Majeſties Command.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON:</hi> Printed by <hi>Henry Hills,</hi> Printer to the King's Moſt Excellent Majeſty, for his Houſhold and Chappel; and are to be ſold at his Printing-Houſe on the Ditch ſide, in <hi>Black-Fryers.</hi> 1687.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb facs="tcp:98331:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:98331:2"/>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>2 TIM. IV. vii.</bibl>
               <q>Bonum certamen certavi, curſum conſum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mavi, fidem ſervavi.</q>
               <q>I have fought a good Fight, conſummated my Race, kept my Faith.</q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>His Character, Moſt Sacred Majeſty, of an undaunted and unwearied Cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage, meeting Victory at laſt through all the Oppoſitions weak Nature can dread, and faint under; of a ſteddy and unalterable fixure in the Reſoluti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on once taken of ſerving God; of an even and punctual Fidelity to his holy Grace; as it is the nobleſt, ſo certainly it doth but Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice either to the great Apoſtle S. <hi>Paul,</hi> or to the great Doctor S. <hi>Auguſtin,</hi> whoſe Feaſt the holy Catholic Church ſolemnizes this day: ſince 'tis given to the firſt by the Holy Ghoſt, moving his Pen, when he writ it, againſt all the Oppoſition his Humility could make; And apply<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to the ſecond by that Church, which is ever guided by the ſame unerring Holy Spirit. 'Tis no wonder one Character ſhould ſerve them both, the one having been ſo exact a Copy of the other. Nature had with an equal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly liberal Hand richly qualified both; Education had re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fined their eminent Parts, by an equally deep Knowledg <note place="margin">Paul<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſaevitia ſil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veſtre erat vitium, ſed magnae fertili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatis erat indici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um. l. 22, c. 70. cont. Fauſt.</note> in all Human Literature; they oppos'd alike the Church of God, the one with the Sword of Perſecution, the other with his ſharper and more dreadful Logic; both
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:98331:3"/> miſ-led by a blind and ſtormy Zeal, which yet argued their Abilities, though miſapplyed. Their Converſion was the immediate Work of Heaven, both being retrieved by its miraculous Voice; their Learning inſpired by the ſame Spirit (though not in a like Degree of Certainty) guided all Chriſtian Divines in the Schools; by their Tongues the Spirit of God ſpoke moſt efficaciouſly in their reſpective Ages, from the Pulpit; their Writings <note place="margin">Numquid hoc eſt intra in gaudium domini tui. <hi>l.</hi> 9. <hi>c.</hi> 10 <hi>conf.</hi>
               </note> have diſarmed all Heretics and Schiſmatics that ever op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed the Church to this Day; by their Apoſtolical La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bors they outwent ſo far all thoſe of their different Ranks, that each could ſay with a juſt Title, I have la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boured more than all; a Love of God frequently heightened into Rapts and Extaſies, equally inflamed both: They both had a Foretaſt here below of Heavenly Bliſs; in a Word, They were <hi>firſt the moſt abſolute mira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culous Conqueſt, and then the moſt victorious Champions of the Grace of God.</hi> That I may the better ſet out S. <hi>Auguſtin</hi> in both theſe Capacities, to Gods greater Glory in him, and to your larger Spiritual Comfort and Benefit (Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Auditors) joyn, I crave, your Prayers with mine to obtain the Succor of that Divine Grace: If I pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume not to preſent them, without taking along the joynt Interceſſion of the Mother of God, I follow there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the Advice of S. <hi>Auguſtin,</hi> which I addreſs to you in his Words; <hi>Let us by the moſt tender Application of our</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Toto mentis affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctu b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>atiſſimae v<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rgin<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>s nos interceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſionibus commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tamus. &amp;c. <hi>Serm.</hi> 35 <hi>de Sa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>c.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>whole Heart, recommend our ſelves to the moſt Bleſſed Virgin's Interceſſion; let us all, with the greateſt eagerneſs, ſtrive to obtain her Protection; that whilſt with Aſſiduity we pay her our Devotions on Earth, ſhe may intreat for us in Heaven by her earneſt Prayers; for undoubtedly ſhe who brought forth the Price of Redemption, hath the greateſt Right to intercede for thoſe who are redeemed.</hi>
            </p>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="3" facs="tcp:98331:3"/>
               <head>Ave Maria.</head>
               <p>LEſt the Offers I ſeem to make at a Panegyric, ſhould dull the Attention of any in my Auditory, led by that common Apprehenſion, Either that Sermons of Saints are like their vulgar Pictures which bear their Names indeed, and ſome Symbols of them, but have in Lieu of their proper natural Features, ſuch only as are borrow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed from the Painters Fancy; or that ſuch ſublime Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues only and rare Gifts of God are treated of in them, as lying far out of the Road and Reach of moſt Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians, are of little Uſe for their Inſtruction and Edifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion: to correct, I ſay, a Miſtake that would ſo far pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>judice, and even defeat my whole Deſign, give me Leave firſt to proteſt, That I will not in this Diſcourſe even hint at any thing concerning this Saint, but what he owns of himſelf in his Writings: His Humility hav<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing prompted him to lay open all his Faults and Weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs in ſome of them; and in others, that Seraphic Love which ever moved his Heart to a grateful Return of Thanks, having often unwarily betrayed what ſingular Graces and Gifts he poſſeſt, <hi>That the Mercy and Juſtice</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">De bonis me<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s, &amp; de malis me<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s Deum la<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>dant, bonum &amp; juſtum, atque in cum ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>citant humanum intellectum &amp; af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectum <hi>l.</hi> 2. retract. c. 6. Non ego ſed gratia Dei mecum.</note> 
                  <hi>of God might receive due Praiſe, and Mens Minds and Hearts be raiſed to give it, by the Knowledg of Gods Favors and of his Sins.</hi> Again, the only Mark I level at, being Gods greater Glory in this his Saint, the Fight and Victory I mean to ſpeak of, is of the Divine Mercy and Grace, ſetting his Free-will in that happy Liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of the Children of God, conquering in and with it; of that Divine Vertue which borrows its greateſt Luſtre from human Weakneſs and Corruption. All therefore that I ſhall offer to your Attention will ſerve for an Encouragement to the very Weakeſt, and ſhew even to thoſe who are fartheſt from God, the Way and Method how to return to him, by yielding them ſelves a Conqueſt to his holy Grace. If I inſiſt much
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:98331:4"/> on thoſe ſtrange Oppoſitions which this bleſſed Saint before his Converſion raiſed within himſelf againſt that Grace which called him to the true Church, and to an eminent degree of Piety in it, I hope it will con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tribute the more to my Auditories Inſtruction and Comfort; for as the Saint himſelf teaches me, <hi>Health</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Confeſs. l. 8. c. 3.</note> 
                  <hi>Creates a greater Joy when reſtored after a deſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate Diſeaſe, and Safety when it ſucceeds the moſt preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing Dangers.—God himſelf is repreſented rejoycing more at the Converſion of one Sinner, than for the perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verance of Ninety Nine Juſt:—And if any part of Holy Writ draws Tears of ſenſible Comfort from our Eyes, and ſoftens our Hearts with a feeling Tenderneſs, 'tis when we read the ſolemn Feaſt in the Houſe of that merciful Father at the Return of his untoward Prodigal Child, who had periſht, and was now found, had been dead, and was now revived.</hi> S. <hi>Auguſtin</hi> till the Age of Thir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty Four Years, was out of the true Church, and Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vor of God, plung'd into Hereſie and Vice. The haughty Perverſeneſs of his Underſtanding ſwell'd up with the proud Conceit of his own Parts, oppoſed it ſelf to Gods Grace, offering the Light of a true Faith: Worldly Intereſt, and the Corruption of his Heart ſwayed by vicious Inclinations, withſtood the ſame Grace, offering the true Comforts of Vertue and Pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ety; Grace conquered at laſt, joyned with his Free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>will, and ſo poſſeſt the whole Soul of <hi>Auguſtin,</hi> that he continued an even Courſe of Vertue the reſt of his Life, by being Faithful to the conquering Grace he had yielded himſelf unto. Theſe two Victories of Gods Grace, bringing <hi>Auguſtin</hi>'s Underſtanding and Heart to a due Submiſſion and conſtant Fidelity, whereby he hath a juſt Claim to my Text; are the two Points of this Diſcourſe, and of Your Royal Majeſties moſt gracious Attention. That true Religion, or the Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip which God requires at our Hand, is ſufficiently <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Jo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>.</hi> 1.</note> revealed to all Mankind, by him who is the Light that enlightens each Man that comes into this World;
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:98331:4"/> that the true Churches Voice, which all are bound to hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Matt.</hi> 16 <hi>&amp;</hi> 18.</note> unto, and obey, may eaſily be heard, and diſtinguiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed; that the Houſe of God, in which alone thoſe Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>craments are diſpenſed, which convey to us a plenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Redemption, and work together with us our Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation, is like a City ſeated on a Hill, expoſed to the View of all; that the Way which God hath markt us out to walk in towards Heaven, is eaſily found out, and followed, ſo that Fools ſhall not go aſtray in it, <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </hi> 35.</note> and conſequently is diſcernible by its Infallible Secu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity; are Truths which Faith teaches us, and even Reaſon evinces to any who ſhall acknowledg in God a Providence and a merciful Goodneſs. How then be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>falls it, that ſo many wander in Darkneſs though ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rounded by that Light, fail to hear this Churches Voice, miſs to ſee this City, err in finding this way? But how could this happen to an <hi>Auguſtin,</hi> ſo that for Twenty Years he ſhould perſevere in an Hereſie the moſt wicked and ſenſeleſs, that ever infected Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind? Some you will ſay are ſtrangely dull, eſpecially in the Concerns of Piety. True, but as the learned <note place="margin">Scientiam Augu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtino coelum dedit ſuper omnes homines, &amp;c. <hi>Avicen.</hi> Feciſſe naturam extremum effe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctum ſine potentiae dum <hi>Auguſtinia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num</hi> creavit ingenium, <hi>Alb. mag.</hi> Confeſſ. l. 4. <hi>c.</hi> 16.</note> World hath ever owned, he had ſo ſoaring and ſearch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing an Underſtanding, that Heaven never gave ſo ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lime a Wit to any Mortal before, ſeeming to exhauſt it's Treaſury in enriching his Mind, Nature at leaſt emptied hers in perfecting him. So few cultivate their Wit by Studies! I allow it; but whoſe was ever po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhed with ſuch Induſtry, improved with ſuch Dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence as S. <hi>Auguſtins?</hi> 
                  <q>What did it avail me, ſaith he of himſelf, that I read and without the help of a Maſter underſtood all the Books that treated of Liberal Sciences, whilſt I remained a dull Slave to my vitious Inclinations? My Back was turned to the true Light, I read by it other things, but ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver caſt back my Eyes to fix them on it. I had a quick and ſharp Wit; it was your Gift my God, but I ſacrificed no Share of it to you; it was a part of my Miſery that I like the prodigal Child had in my
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:98331:5"/> own Hands and proper Diſpoſal, that rich Portion of my Inheritance, whilſt I uſed not thoſe Abili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties in your Service, but withdrew from you my God into a foreign Land.</q> Poſſibly being born and bred up in Error, he met with none that could lay it open to him: On the contrary, he was born of a moſt pious Catholic Mother, he had felt in his Youth moſt preſſing Inclinations to Piety, he had ſince heard the ableſt Divines of Gods Church in <hi>Africa</hi> and <hi>Italy.</hi> Perhaps he was little concerned to find out the Truth, and little regarded the Proofs of it that were offered him: he aſſures us that for Eleven years at leaſt, he <note place="margin">Immortalitatem ſapientlae concu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>bam aeſtu cordis incredibili, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> c. <hi>conf. l</hi> 3. <hi>c.</hi> 4<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </note> burnt with an incredible Deſire of the Knowledg of Eternal Truth, which during that Time buoyed him up and raiſed him toward the God he ſought. <q>That he eagerly wiſhed for Wings to quit this World, and ſoar to that true Wiſdom which dwells only in God, All this perchance was only a vain Curioſity in one, who felt no Senſe of Piety, no Spark of Devotion: My Heart, ſays he, had ſuckt in with my Mothers <note place="margin">Ibidem.</note> Milk, a tender Devotion for the Name of my Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deemer, it had ſunk deeply there, what ever I read of the Name of Jeſus was not ſet in it, how ſmooth and learned it ever were, ſeemed inſipid and reliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed not.</q> It may be that he refuſed to uſe Means pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portioned to the finding of the Truth: No, he neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lected but one, he uſed all the reſt. <q>If reading be uſeful to that End, he left no Book unread; if con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſulting private Men, he dealt with the moſt eminent of all perſwaſions, and was deceived by ſome who had always in their Mouths <hi>the Lord, the Spirit, the Truth:</hi> Such were their Words, ſays he, but their Heart <note place="margin">Confeſ. l. 3. c. 5.</note> was empty; my Soul did inwardly ſigh to thee my God, whilſt they deceived me with an Empty Sound of thy Name.—Unhappy me, by what large Steps did I ſink into the depth of Hell!</q> But ſure he read not the Holy. Text of Scripture: He did, but to little Purpoſe, <hi>Behold,</hi> ſays he, <hi>I ſaw there ſomething covered</hi>
                  <pb n="7" facs="tcp:98331:5"/> 
                  <hi>and vailed to the Proud, and not open, not naked to Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren:</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Ecce video <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> non comp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>rta<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> ſuperbis, neque nudatam pueris, ſed inceſſu humi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem ſucceſſu ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>celſa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> &amp; velatam myſteriis, &amp;c. ibidem.</note> 
                  <hi>Low in appearance, but that ſoared high, and was wrapped up in Myſteries: The Light it gave, might have increaſed and grown with a little one, but I diſdained to be a little One:</hi> That is, I ſcorned to be taught my Book, to hear any Interpreter of it. Bleſſed God! ſuch Parts employed! ſuch Means uſed! ſo long a Search ſo ſtudiouſly continued! and diſcovered he not <note place="margin">Inveniri poſſe viam vitae minim<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> putabam. Conf. l. 6 c. 1.</note> the true Religion? So far from it, that he acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledges he came to be of no Religion, and even to doubt whether God had aſſigned any Way to eternal Life, which could be found out. Were it poſſible to diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver what blockt up his Way in the ſearch after Truth? I obſerve in him three Letts that perfectly obſtructed it. <hi>Firſt,</hi> He was prepoſſeſt with a fixed Perſwaſion, <note place="margin">L. 4. Conf. c. 10, &amp; 13.</note> That the Catholic Church had erred. He began to ſuſpect, and even to hate the Heretics, of whoſe Congregation he was; yet they being many, their Mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude retarded his Diligence in enquiring farther, <hi>Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he deſpaired that Truth could be found in your Church, O Lord of Heaven and Earth.</hi> Such was the Averſion from it they had prevented him with. <hi>You brought me to Ambroſe without any Knowledg in me of your Deſign,</hi> ſays he, <hi>which was, that by true Knowledg he might bring me to you; I loved and valued him, but not as a Teacher of Truth; for I deſpaired of finding any ſuch in your Church. Secondly,</hi> Beſides that general Prejudice he nouriſht, he miſrepreſented to himſelf the particular Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nets of the Church, and then hated and reviled the ug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Idol of his own carving. <hi>If ever,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>my Soul lifted up and moved her ſelf towards the Catholic Faith, I was ſoon driven back; for alas! Catholic Faith was not that which I took it to be. Thirdly,</hi> He was willing to be convinced, but not to believe; to ſee, but not to ſubmit his Underſtanding to Faith: He ſought a clear Evidence, and ſuch as ſhould not controul his uſual Apprehenſion, or oppoſe his Senſes, as if they had been fit Judges of the Objects of Faith, revealed Truths.
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:98331:6"/> 
                  <hi>My ſick Soul,</hi> ſays he, <hi>could not be cured but by Believ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing,</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Valetudo animae meae quae utique niſi credendo ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nari non poterat, ne falſa crederet ſanari recuſabat, &amp;c. Conf. l. 6. c. 1.</note> 
                  <hi>and for fear of being ſurprized, and made to believe what might be falſe, I refuſed to admit of a Cure; I was reſolved either to ſee things, or if I could not, to conceive them as evidently as that Seven and Three make up Ten.</hi> It was on theſe his Three miſtaken Methods that he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flected afterwards, when ſighing he ſaid, <hi>What am I</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Quid ſum ego mihi ſine te niſi dux in praeceps, &amp; quis homo eſt quilibet homo cum ſit homo! Conf. l. 1. c. 4.</note> 
                  <hi>to my ſelf but a Guide leading into a Precipice? What a ſad Man, is each Man, when he is but one Man?</hi> That is, when he is left to his own Private Senſe, abandon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to his own Judgment. Was it poſſible that Gods Grace, had it been leſs than Omnipotent, ſhould pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vail againſt theſe ſtubborn Ill-diſpoſitions of his Mind? Long was the Combat, violent the Strife, but Grace conquered at laſt, and by this Method gained the Field. <hi>Firſt,</hi> God by a particular Light convinced him, That <note place="margin">L 7. conf. c. 5.</note> Religion was not Opinion, but Faith; not a calling of things Divine to the Teſt of our weak Judgment, and carnal Senſes; but a captivating of our Under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding, and humbly ſacrificing it to the Divine Truth. <hi>Next,</hi> he obſerved how numerable thoſe things were, which he believed, though he had never ſeen them; How he had ever adored God, and owned his Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, though he knew not what a Kind of Subſtance he was, nor what Way led unto or from him. <hi>I thought on theſe Things,</hi> ſays he, <hi>and you were preſent to me, I was carried away by reſtleſs Waves, and you governed and ſteered my Courſe, I ſighed, and you heard me. Then</hi> he reſolves to ſeek more narrowly. <q>Let Time be aſſigned, ſays he, let ſome Hours be al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lotted <note place="margin">Ibidem. c. 11.</note> to the Study of that great Science, How I ſhall ſave my Soul. Let all Vain and Empty Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerns periſh, and all my Thoughts and Endeavors be ſpent in the ſole Purſuit of Truth; this Life at beſt is but Toylſome and Miſerable, Death certain and at Hand, if it ſurprizes whither do we go?</q> He preſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly applyed himſelf ſeriouſly to an humble Search after a Guide to Truth; when favoured with a new Light
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:98331:6"/> from Heaven, he cryes out, <hi>Conceive better Hopes my Soul, the Catholic Faith doth not teach what we Believe, and fondly accuſed her of.</hi> Thus diſpoſed, and weigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing with a due Attention the Articles of the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholic Belief, he owns his Heart was filled with Joy, and his Face covered with Shame, to ſee how profanely he had ſtrove ſo many Years, not againſt Catholic Faith, as he conceived, but againſt his own Dreams, how Raſh he had been, and equally Impious: <hi>That whereas he ſhould with Submiſſion have learnt from the</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>o quippe teme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rarius &amp; impius fueram, quod ea quae debebam quaerenda diſcere, accuſando dixe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ram. <hi>l.</hi> 6. <hi>Conf.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Church, that which ſhe held, he faſtened on her what he pleaſed, and accuſed her of it.</hi> He reads next Holy Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture, with the due deference he owed to that Churches Interpretation, owning there is no Text of Scripture into which a falſe Gloſs may not Foiſt an Error; that the Letter ever kills, when ſevered from the Spirit <note place="margin">Nulla ſcriptura eſt quae non apud illos qui cam non intelligunt, poſſit reprehendi. <hi>l.</hi> 1. <hi>de gen. contra Manich.</hi>
                  </note> which ought to quicken; that the very miſapplying a Text, otherwiſe truly Interpreted, is the moſt dangerous Weapon that a tempting Devil could uſe, to deceive, even if poſſible, Truth it ſelf, with an <hi>It is written;</hi> that ſtub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bornly to maintain our own Fancy to be the Word of God, becauſe we uphold it by a forced Text, is to ſet up the greateſt Abomination of Deſolation in the Houſe of God, an Idol upon his Altar; and to adore it by the worſt of Idolatries, Self-worſhip; proudly challenging as our own, what Chriſt only could bequeath, and left to his Church, to each Member as united to the whole, the Spirit of Truth, who alone muſt Interpret what he Dicta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted alone: On which ſcore Chriſt left as a <hi>Depoſitum</hi> in the ſame Hands of the Church, the Letter and the Spirit, the Book and the Senſe, the Word and the Truth, to be delivered to all ſucceeding Ages by the ſame Authority, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the ſeparating of the one from the other, would <note place="margin">Neque enim na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tae ſunt haereſes niſi dum ſcriptu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rae bonae intelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guntur non bene, &amp; quod in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>is non bene Intelligitur etiam temeré &amp; audacter aſſeritur. <hi>Tract.</hi> 18. <hi>in Jo.</hi>
                  </note> turn the moſt wholſom Food of our Souls to preſent Poi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon; whence Hereſies have had their birth, from good Scriptures ill underſtood, and from the bold and raſh aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerting of ſuch Errors. So that this only is the holy Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thod to be followed, that what we find in Scripture con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formable
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:98331:7"/> with the Faith we have received, we feed on it; but when any part thereof appears not uniform with that Rule, that it create in us no Doubts, but only an humble <note place="margin">Quod ſecundum ſanam ſidei regu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lam intelligere non poterimus, dubitationem a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feramus, intelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gentiam diſſera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus. <hi>Ibid.</hi>
                  </note> perſuaſion that we underſtand not yet ſuch a Scripture. He had ſcarce receiv'd this Light, when behold all his Doubts raiſed before by the ſame Lecture, diſappeared, all thoſe ſeeming Contradictions vaniſhed; whence he was per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectly convinced, that the Catholic Church was the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erring Guide to be followed by all the Diſciples of Chriſt. He expreſſes the difference of this preſent Submiſſion, from that former Search into Scripture without this Guide, under the Compariſon of two Travellers, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of <note place="margin">Aliud eſt de ſil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veſtri cacumine videre pat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>iam pacis, &amp; iter ad cam non invenire &amp; fruſtra con<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ri per invia: aliud viam tenere illuc ducentem cura coeleſtis impera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>toris munitam. <hi>Conf. l.</hi> 8. <hi>c.</hi> 1.</note> of the one climbs up a high Tree indeed, and ſees thence the Place he would go to, but then ranges<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> blindly in the thick Wood; whilſt the other walks ſecurely in a Way leading right thither, without fear or danger of going aſtray; a large Royal Way, made and kept by the Providence of the King of Heaven. Then obſerving how all pious humble Catholics, tho' never ſo plain and illiterate Men, enjoyed as a Birthright that Happineſs, the Search whereof had been ſo dangerous, the Purchaſe ſo painful to him; What <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Lib.</hi> 8. <hi>cap.</hi> 1. <hi>Conf.</hi>
                  </note> want, O Lord (ſaid he,) what want did your Little-ones feel of a deep and quick Wit? How much did this Dull<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of theirs injure them? <hi>Whilſt they were carried in your</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Catholica delici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>tur Eccleſia &amp; dicat ego do<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>mio &amp; cor meum vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gilat. Quid eſt, niſi, ita qui<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſco <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> audiam. <hi>Tract.</hi> 25. <hi>in Jo.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Arms, and reſted in the Neſt of the Catholic Church, enlarg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Wings of their Charity, and ſtrengthning them by the Food of a ſound Faith;</hi> choſen for, and brought to them without their labor? <hi>Happy Men, who enjoy a perfect Reſt, while their whole Duty is to hearken.</hi> Behold the final Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctory of Grace over the Pride of Human Wit, captivated to Faith, our Self ſufficiency humbled under the Tutor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Diſcipline and Direction of the Church. No wonder if this Saint afterwards us'd no other Method in reconci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling miſled Heretics to Truth, but that by which Gods Grace had retrieved him from his Errors, the infallible Authority of a Guiding Church. He adviſed Unlearned Men in general, to relie altogether, and lean on the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Epiſt<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                     </hi> 56,</note> of the Church: He minded the moſt Learned,
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:98331:7"/> who feared to be deceived, where Truth ſeemed to them <note place="margin">Fo. 7. li<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> contra creſco. c. 33.</note> but obſcurely revealed, to conſult the Church, which the holy Scriptures point out without ambiguity; aſſuring them, that (even in Fundamental Articles, of as immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ate neceſſity as Baptiſm is, where Scripture mentions no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing thereof) <hi>the very Truth of Scriptures is followed, whilſt that is done which the Catholic Church declares for,</hi> and with reaſon, ſince we receive, ſaid he, the Books of the Old and New Teſtament in the ſame number that the Authority of <note place="margin">Fo. 10. Serm. 191. de tempore.</note> the Catholic Church hath Sealed and Delivered up to us; ſince <hi>I would not give any credit to the Goſpel, if the Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Fo. 6. l. contra Epiſt. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>und. c. 5.</note> 
                  <hi>of the Catholic Church moved me not to it: whatever Doubts there ariſe, not to yield to the Church, 'tis the utmoſt</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Ad honor. de u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>til. Cred. c. 17. Fo. 6.</note> 
                  <hi>Impiety, the moſt looſe Arrogancy:</hi> 
                  <q>For whether in her moſt general, neceſſary and firſt Principles, or in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moteſt Truths leading to ſolid Devotion; whether in <note place="margin">Contra Fauſt. l 15. c. 3. in Fo. 6.</note> her Milk or in her Bread; the Church alone poſſeſſes Truth. Thoſe then who have their Belief yet to chooſe, who begin a ſerious Search into Religion, deſiring to <note place="margin">De util. Cred. c. 7. &amp; 8.</note> know to which they are to commit their Souls for In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction, they muſt, without any Doubt, begin with the Catholic Church: If they have been wavering in their Mind, and deſire to put an end to their toil in ſeeking, let them follow the Way of Catholic Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pline, which as it is derived from Jeſus Chriſt to us <note place="margin">Chriſtus miracu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lis conc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>liavit au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctoritatem aucto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritate meruit ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dem. De util. cred. c. 14.</note> by the Apoſtles, ſo muſt it be tranſmitted to our Poſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity in ſucceeding Ages.</q> We muſt receive our Faith from that Church, as the firſt converted to Chriſtianity received it from the Apoſtles, and they from Chriſt. Her Authority being once eſtabliſhed by the ſame Proofs which <note place="margin">Domino coope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rante &amp; ſermo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem confirmante ſequent b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nis. Marc. ult.</note> the Apoſtles offered for theirs, our whole Work is to em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brace what God teaches by her Voice, tho' it be above the level and reach of Human Reaſon: <q>For before our Minds be cleared from that Dullneſs which Sin hath left <note place="margin">De agone Chron. c. 13.</note> in it, that eſpecially of Inſidelity, we muſt believe what we cannot yet underſtand, the Prophet having moſt truly ſaid, <hi>Without you believe, you ſhall not underſtand;</hi> for Faith is delivered in the Church in very few words, in
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:98331:8"/> which Eternal Myſteries are comprehended, which car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal man cannot yet conceive. The firſt Hereſie aroſe <note place="margin">In Pſalm.</note> amongſt Chriſt's Diſciples from the refuſal of yielding to his words, which ſeemed hard, they unhappily made a Schiſm from him: If <hi>Peter</hi> ſtuck ſtedfaſt to Chriſt, was it by underſtanding the high Myſteries of that Speech of Chriſt? No; but <hi>he piouſly believed what he un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">In Pſalm 130.</note> 
                     <hi>not: Learn, little ones of Chriſt, learn from hence due Piety;</hi> for thoſe who will diſpute of Myſteries they do not underſtand, do but heighten their Pride, whil'ſt that curſe falls on them which the Royal Prophet ſpeaks of in the 130 <hi>Pſalm,</hi> If I was not humble of heart, but have ſwelled up my mind with Pride, as the Child weaned from the breaſt is towards his Mother, ſo be my Soul puniſhed. The Church of God is that Mother from which they are ſevered; they ſhould have been nurs'd and fed by her, and ſo might have grown and become capable of digeſting the Word and Myſteries of Faith. Ponder then well the ſenſe of thoſe two words of your Creed, <hi>Catholic Church;</hi> obſerve what a certain death <note place="margin">Pſalm in part. Donati.</note> ſeizes the Vine-branch, how it withers when lopt off from the Body of the Vine; come and ſeek Life from the Root; number the Prieſts in St. <hi>Peter</hi>'s Chair; obſerve how they have ſucceeded to one another: that's the Rock which the proud Gates of Hell never conquer.</q> This was his method of reducing thoſe better-diſpoſed Souls which erred by miſtake rather than by malice; but if he found any obdurate, before he ſhaked againſt them the duſt of his feet, according to Chriſt's Command, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he avoided them as already condemned, following the Apoſtles Counſel; he with a true Charity, weeping <note place="margin">Ad Tit. 3. 10.</note> for the certain danger they ran, minded them of it thus: <hi>To be fond of ones proper Opinion, or to be averſe</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">L. 2. con. Don. c. 5.</note> 
                  <hi>from better, to that degree as to be guilty, by breaking Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion, of the Sacrilege of Schiſm or Hereſie, is a Preſum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ption beyond all others, but the Devils;</hi> ſince it is to refuſe a Submiſſion to the Spirit of Truth, guiding that Church it is promiſed unto, and which God commands all to
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:98331:8"/> hearken unto, and to obey. 'Tis the Crime of <hi>Corah,</hi> erecting an Altar againſt an Altar, which involves the weak and ignorant Followers as much as the Leaders, when equally ſtubborn in ſtanding to their Separation; it ſeeming even a higher Crime in unlearned men, who pretend not to extraordinary Parts, and yet preſume to be Judges of, and to condemn the Univerſal Church, preferring to her Deciſions the oppoſite Errors of a few <note place="margin">L. de Bapt. con Donat. c. 16. L. 2. contra c. 23.</note> of her revolted Children. I do not deſpair of the Salvation of any one in particular, whether he be a great Sinner in the Church, or a Schiſmatic out of it. Judgment is reſerved to God alone; he only who hath in his hands the Iron Rod, can break the Earthen Veſſels: but I equally de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare of both, with the Apoſtle, That neither thoſe who in the true Church die in ſin, nor thoſe who through a ſtiff ſtubbornneſs die out of her Communion, ſhall be ſaved. <note place="margin">De ſymb. ad Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>techum. c 10.</note> 
                  <q>For whoever ſhall be found out of it, will be an Alien, not reckoned amongſt the Children of God, whom he ſhall not have for Father, having refuſed to have the Church for his Mother. That Catholic Church which only is the Body of Chriſt, of which He is the <note place="margin">Tract. 32. ſup. Joan. <hi>Salvator corpo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>is ſui,</hi> L. de verâ &amp; falſ. poen. c. 12.</note> Head, whereof He alone is the Savior; out of that Body no one receives Life from God's Holy Spirit, nor conſequently can pretend to an Eternal one. <hi>Out of this Churches <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity no one can attain to true Penance;</hi> no one can obtain remiſſion of ſins, (her Children alone being the ſole Diſpenſers of the Myſteries of God.) In Her Houſe only the Lamb is eaten; that is, on Her Altars only is ſacrificed the true Victim of our Redeem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, <note place="margin">Ser. 18<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>. de tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pore.</note> (which alone ſo applies to us the ſaving Sacrifice of the Croſs, that who eats not of that Fleſh hath no Life in him.) <hi>As then no one eſcaped the Deluge, who was not</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">Q. Q. 75. ad <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>. Q 52. Contra Petili, ut ſupra.</note> 
                     <hi>in</hi> Noah<hi>'s Ark, ſo no one ſhall be ſaved, who is not a Member of the Church, out of which an Heretic may have all things but Salvation:</hi> He may have the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, he may keep the Goſpel, he may have the Faith; and preach it, only Salvation he cannot have. Tho' he be a <hi>Paul</hi> converted by God's Voice, inſtructed from
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:98331:9"/> Heaven, he muſt firſt be ſent to thoſe who can admini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter to him the Sacraments, and enter him a Member into the Church's Body. Tho' he be a pious <hi>Cornelius,</hi> an Alms-giver, a man of Prayer, a ſober Liver; tho' he have an Angel to inſtruct him, <hi>Peter</hi> muſt teach him, and admit him into the Kingdom of God upon Earth, of which he hath the Keys, (the Church) before he <note place="margin">Ad Bonifacium cont. 2. Ep. Pelag.</note> can be ſaved: otherwiſe, let him obſerve all the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandments, live a chaſt life to the purity of an entire Virginity, be profuſe in Alms-giving, moſt patient in bearing with all Injuries; let him ſell all, and give to the Poor, reſerving nothing for himſelf: <hi>after all thoſe</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">De fide ad Pet. c. 39.</note> 
                     <hi>ſeemingly laudable actions, yet if he be not of the true and Catholic Faith, when he departs this life he will meet a cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain Damnation, altho' he ſhould ſhed his Blood for the Name of Chriſt.</hi> Say not that <hi>Cyprian</hi> and his Church, becauſe they condemned no man, and ſeparated none from their Communion, were not Heretics, and that it may ſuffice you that you copy this Example: That was enough when the Church had not yet decided the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpute, to whoſe Deciſion <hi>Cyprian</hi> had certainly ſubmit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted himſelf, and with her condemned all her Oppoſers, which you do not. Say not that you err in no <hi>Funda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentals;</hi> that you conceive it a thing indifferent unto what Party you joyn your ſelves, ſuppoſing they be <note place="margin">Epiſtola 45. de Donatiſtis.</note> Chriſtians, and therefore remain fixed to that Party in which you were born: for whatſoever in particular the Opinions of Heretics and Schiſmatics be, ſince they pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs otherwiſe than the Church does, and requires of <note place="margin">Serm. 14. de ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bis Dom.</note> them to do, they are in a ſtate of Damnation, becauſe <hi>they renounce thereby one fundamental Article of Faith, the</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">In Pſal. 17. <hi>In ventre Eccleſiae veritas manet, quiſquis ab hoc ſepara<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>us fuerit, neceſſe eſt ut falſa loquatur.</hi>
                     </note> 
                     <hi>Authority and <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity of the Catholic Church, in whoſe bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſom Truth dwells.</hi> So that whoſoever is removed from it, 'tis neceſſary that he be in Error. Say not, I am ſatisfied, my conſcience doth not reproach me that I am in an Error.</q> I am charitably perſuaded others may alſo ſerve God well; but many Myſteries in the Catholic Church appearing to me very ſtrange, how can I believe
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:98331:9"/> what I underſtand not? or how ſhall I, an unlearned perſon, ever ſatisfie my ſelf of the Truth? 'Tis then better for me to live of that Religion my Father and Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther were of, and die in that Church which I was Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtned in. Such weak reaſons, which yet retain in Hereſie the greateſt part of thoſe who are unhappily engaged in it, betray equally the weakneſs of their Judgment, and headſtrong ſtubbornneſs of their Will. The whole Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholic Church of all Ages, of all Nations, in her General Councils, reſts ſatisfied of the Truth of each Article of Catholic Belief, ſo as to Curſe and Excommunicate all thoſe who believed as you do, in oppoſition to her. Now <note place="margin">Sunt ibi quaeda<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> q<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ae ſuboffendunt animo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>naros &amp; negligentes ſui, qu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> maxima tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ba eſt; popula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riter accuſarl poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſunt, defendi au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem populariter, propter myſte<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>a quae his continen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur, non à multis a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>modum poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſunt. <hi>c.</hi> 2. <hi>de util. Cred.</hi>
                  </note> there is an eaſe and ſatisfaction which proceeds from Ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norance, (ſuch as is in him who in a dark night walks without fear on the brim of a Precipice he knows nothing of) another from Knowledge; and can you think, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the higheſt Preſumption, that Ignorance lay on the whole Church's ſide, and Science in your private Gift? Is it charity to think all thoſe General Councils were moſt uncharitable, which all ſaid <hi>Anathema</hi> to the Errors which they condemned, and you now approve? <q>True Faith involves Myſteries which uſually ſcandalize igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant Souls, and careleſs in ſeeking Inſtruction, that is, the greateſt part of the World, becauſe <hi>they can be plauſibly argued againſt, but not ſo eaſily made clear, they would not otherwiſe be Myſteries of Faith.</hi> 'Tis then not only moſt to be counſell'd, to believe what you ſee not <note place="margin">Credere ante ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tione, cum perci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piendae rationi non ſis idoneus, &amp; ipſa <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>e exco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lere animum ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipiendi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> ſemini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus ventatis, non ſolum ſaluberri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mum judico; ſed tale ſine quo aegris anim<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap> 
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>alus redi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re non poteſt.</note> yet the reaſon of, ſince you acknowledge your ſelf un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>learned, ignorant, not able to judge in ſuch Debates; and by Faith to manure your Soul, and to fit it to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive and improve the Seed of Truth: but 'tis ſo abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutely neceſſary, that by no other method health can be reſtored to a ſick mind. Are you ignorant? not able by your own Judgment to determin on what ſide the Truth lies?</q> Why then 'tis evident that you are bound to leave all thoſe Congregations which leave you to your own final Deciſion, and to repair to that Church which alone gives you an Infallible Guide. <q>Think well of God's infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:98331:10"/> mercy, and true deſire that you ſhould be ſaved, and <hi>never deſpair to find an Authority eſtabliſhed by God</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">Non eſt deſperan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dum ab codem ipſo Deo auctori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatem aliquam conſtitutam<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> qua v<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>lut certo gradu innitentes at<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lamur ad Deum. Epiſt. 56. Immo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bili authoritati.</note> 
                     <hi>himſelf, from which, as from a ſecure ſtep, we may take our riſe to God.</hi> Heretics offer Reaſons and Arguments for proof of their Belief, and pretend by them to be preferr'd to the <hi>unmovable Authority of the Church,</hi> which is ſo firmly eſtabliſhed; therein lies the raſhneſs com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon to all Heretics: But the moſt meek Lord of our Faith hath been pleaſed to ſtrengthen his Church with an Authority far weightier than that of all others; into this Caſtle of the Faith all the weaker ought to with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>draw <note place="margin">Vere illa rectiffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ma diſciplina eſt in aciem fidei quam maxime recipi infirmos ut pro illis jam fictiſſime poſitis, firmiſſima ratio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne pugnetur.</note> themſelves, whil'ſt for them, thus ſecure, others fight with invincible Reaſons and Proofs.</q> You are willing to be guided by ſo weak an Authority as that of your Father and Mother; and will you refuſe to be gui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded by the pious Examples of all their Anceſtors, and of the whole Church for fourteen hundred years? <q>As for your Baptiſm, in it you were chriſtened a Catholic, whoever baptized you; and by declaring your ſelf a Catholic, you reſtore your ſelf to the Religion you were chriſtened in: For the Catholic Church is like un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Paradiſe, the Waters of whoſe Fountain could be drunk out of it in the Rivers that ſtreamed out; but that Baptiſm being given and belonging only to the Catholic Church, <hi>as in Paradiſe only could be enjoyed temporal hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſs,</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">Salutem beatitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinis extra cam neminem vel per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipere vel tenere. <hi>De bapt. cont.</hi> Don. l. 4. c. 2.</note> 
                     <hi>ſo no one purchaſes or maintains a Right to eternal happineſs out of that Church.</hi>
                  </q> Thus did this holy Saint endeavor to draw back to the true Church's Communion thoſe more ſtubborn Heretics, creating in them that holy Fear of God, which is the beginning of Wiſdom. Chriſtian Brethren, you who are ſo happy as to have been born in, or early called to the Boſom of this holy Catholic Church, and thereby to enjoy that Bleſſing with leſs toil and labor than it coſt S. <hi>Auguſtin;</hi> Be ever thankful for ſo great a Mercy; wonder not when you ſee knowing Men, ſober Enquirers, who, even after a ſtudious ſearch, have ſo thick a Veil yet over their eyes, as not to ſee thoſe glorious evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent Marks God hath diſtinguiſhed this Church by, nor
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:98331:10"/> their Obligation of rendring themſelves Members of it. For twenty years <hi>Auguſtin,</hi> a man of far greater Parts, and a more diligent Searcher, was thus blind. Pity thoſe <note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> who pin their Faith on the Sleeve, bottom it on the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority of ſome ſuch particular men, whil'ſt they refuſe to give ear to the whole Catholic Church, which aſſures them that they go aſtray. Pray for both, obtain a Ray of Grace for them, and they will ſee as you do, judge as you do, and equally bleſs God for it. If any here pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent enjoy not yet that happineſs, may the Example and Motives of this Saint's Converſion prevail with him. Let him weigh whether he be not unhappily under the ſame prejudices this Saint was ſo long prepoſſeſs'd with. <q>'Tis in vain to conſult many Books or Perſons on each point of Belief: Alas! ſays the Saint, taught by twenty years <note place="margin">De Doctrina Ch. c. 16.</note> experience, the helps of all ſorts of Inſtructions recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved from Man avail little, if God work not in us that very effect which we expect from them.</q> Seek, then, Knowledge from God by a devout and humble Prayer, but expect not that he ſhould give you a new Revelation, or lead you to Truth, but by thoſe Guides his admirable Providence hath provided for you. Reſolve your Faith finally into God's Word; but that you may not be decei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, hear it from the Mouth, receive it by the Authority of that Church you are commanded to hearken unto. Thus did this holy Doctor, offering to thoſe Heretics, who queſtioned the Grounds of his Faith, theſe evident Marks by which God hath character'd his Church, that Pillar of Truth on which all the Faithful are to lean. If any ſtubbornly refuſe to obſerve them, they will allow me however to offer them to the Catholic part of my Audi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tory for their comfort. <q>This is then the account he gives of his own and our Faith: <hi>Many things do moſt juſtly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">In Epiſt. Fund. cap. 4, &amp; 5.</note> 
                     <hi>me in the Boſom of the Catholic Church; Firſt, the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion in Faith, and conſent of many Nations.</hi> 'Tis the common miſery of all Heretics not to ſee what of all things <note place="margin">Fo. 2. l. 7. contra Parmen. c. 3.</note> in the world is moſt patent, and ſeated in the very eyes of all Nations, to wit the Church; out of the Unity
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:98331:11"/> whereof, whatever they do, can no more cover their Souls from the anger of God, than a Cobweb could pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve their Bodies from cold. That Church which eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry-where <note place="margin">1. de Symbol<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> cap. 5.</note> oppoſing different Hereſies, can never be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quered by them. They all went out of Her, like unto ſo many withered Branches cut off from, and caſt out of the Vine, whil'ſt She remains in her own Vine, ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hering to her own Root, enjoying her Charity, or per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect <note place="margin">Tract. 3. in Ep. Joann.</note> Union. In her alone we hold the Inheritance of Chriſt (all Nations:) They have it not whoſe Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion unites not the <hi>whole Circle of the Earth;</hi> who is not in Communion with that Inheritance, is gone out of it: Such may challenge Chriſt, but to as little purpoſe as he who in the Goſpel made this addreſs to him; Say, O <note place="margin">Serm. de temp. 169.</note> Lord, to my Brother, that he divide the Inheritance with me: Chriſt refuſed to divide it amongſt them. <hi>Paul</hi> was as great an Enemy to Diviſion, when he ſaid, I beg of you, Brethren, that you ſay all of you the ſame thing, and that there be no Schiſms amongſt you: He wept for thoſe, who, tho' on his account, divided Chriſt. <hi>See then how wicked thoſe men are who will be divided!</hi> They <note place="margin">Brevic. contra Donatiſtas. Acutum aliquid ſibi dicere viden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur cum Catholi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cae nomen non ex totius Orbis com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munione inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pretantur, ſed ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervatione Praece<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptorum omn<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>um. L. contra Parm. multa Fruſta de Uno Frnſto.</note> think themſelves witty, when ſeeing their Congrega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion reſtrained within the bounds of ſome Province or Kingdom, they pretend that they be <hi>a part of the Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lic Church,</hi> that hath all things commanded and neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry for Salvation, as if to be a Catholic did not import a Communion or Unity in Faith <hi>and Sacraments,</hi> in a Church diffuſed the whole World over. They cut off a part, and that again falls into many pieces, tho' <hi>no ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity can warrant a rent from the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity,</hi> tho' Chriſt's Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment was ſeamleſs, and fell to the Lot of one, becauſe all that belong to it are gathered into a perfect Unity: No, the Catholic Church is but one; <hi>it cannot be divided, nor</hi> 
                     <note place="margin">Eccleſia Catholica eſt una, non poteſt eſſe diviſa nec ſciſſa in diverſas partes. Epiſt. 47. Dicendum eſt quae ve<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> ubi ſit una Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſia quia praeter unam altera non eſt. L. 1. cont. Don.</note> 
                     <hi>cut into different parts:</hi> And, Where is that Church? ought to be our ſole Quaere; for beſides that One, there is not another. It is in thoſe good, faithful, and true Servants of God, where-ever diffuſed, joyned not only by a Spiritual Union, but in the ſame Communion of
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:98331:11"/> Sacraments; whereas all the Congregations, or rather Diviſions, which call themſelves Churches of Jeſus Chriſt, and which are divided from, and oppoſite to one another, and Enemies to <hi>the Congregation of <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity,</hi> which <note place="margin">Spirituall Unitate devinctis in ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dem <hi>Communione Sacramen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>orum</hi> de Bapt. contra Don. l. 7. c 51. Si noſtra Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munio eſt Eccleſia Chriſti, veſtra Communio non eſt Eccleſia Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſti, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Serm. 11. de ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bis Dom. cap. 23. Qui ad Religio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num, ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>iſſ <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>s tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>cunt, cont. C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>eſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>. l 3.</note> is the true Church, belong not to Her, tho' they bear her Name; they might belong to her if the Holy Ghoſt were divided againſt himſelf. We may then ſay to each, <hi>If thoſe of Our Communion be the Church of Chriſt, thoſe of Yours be not the Church of Chriſt:</hi> For which-ever be the Church of Chriſt, 'tis but ONE, of which 'tis ſaid, <hi>One</hi> is my <hi>Dove.</hi> I will then never hear thoſe who lead to a Diviſion of Religions or Churches, ſaying <hi>Here</hi> is Chriſt, and <hi>There</hi> is Chriſt. <hi>Secondly, I am kept in that Church by her Authority, grounded on Miracles, led by Hope,</hi> (that Hope which moves the Members of that Church to pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſe Eternal Glory, promiſed as a Reward by our juſt Judge to meritorious Actions) <hi>increaſed by Charity. Thirdly, becauſe that Authority of Hers is back'd by her conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuation and Antiquity;</hi>
                  </q> all other Congregations having had their decay long ſince, or their beginning ſo lately, that their preciſe Age, the place of their Birth, the very names of their Fathers, are known; whil'ſt She, founded on the Prince of the Apoſtles, with an infallible promiſe, That <note place="margin">Matt. 16.</note> the Gates of Hell ſhall never prevail againſt Her, That Chriſt will ever dwell in Her, hath continued theſe ſeven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teen Ages defended from Error by him whoſe Sanctity and Mercy could not otherwiſe have abſolutely commanded us to ſubmit to her Direction, under the pain of belonging as little to him as the very Heathens. <hi>Fourthly, by the Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſion of Prieſts in the Seat of</hi> Peter <hi>to this preſent Biſhop.</hi> Behold the Title <hi>Roman,</hi> importing a continued Succeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of 244 Teachers legally ſent from God, an Union with the Paſtor of the <hi>one only Flock,</hi> the Vicar of Chriſt; <hi>whoſe</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Roma reſponſa vene<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>unt cauſa <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ita eſt atinam error finiatur.</note> 
                  <hi>Authority is ſo Sacred, that in differences about Religion, when he has paſt Sentence, the caſe is out of queſtion, tho' the Error continue; ſo unerring, at leaſt when that Voice of the Church is owned by her repreſentative Body, that if an Angel from</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Fo. 7. in Pſal. cont. part. Don. &amp; To. 2. Ep. 164.</note> 
                  <hi>Heaven ſhould require from us to abandon the Church in which</hi>
                  <pb n="20" facs="tcp:98331:12"/> 
                  <hi>that Succeſſion is found, we ought to return him no other Anſwer but an</hi> Anathema. <hi>In fine, the very name of Catholic detains me in her Communion,</hi> &amp;c. <q>A Name <hi>She</hi> only hath ever own<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed! Such was the Bleſſed Saint's Profeſſion of Faith, a Record of Truth thirteen Ages old, and ſo plain and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vincing, that he doubted not to addreſs himſelf thus to the diſſenting Sectaries of his time: <hi>Can we</hi> be unwilling <note place="margin">Fo. 6. de Util. Cred. c. 17.</note> and ſlow to repair to the Boſom of that Church, which hath ever been maintained <hi>in the height of an abſolute Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority,</hi> even by the general acknowledgment and conſent of all Mankind, by the continual Succeſſion of Biſhops in the See Apoſtolic, againſt the oppoſition raiſed by ſo great a number of Hereſies, which have bark'd in vain againſt her, and which have been condemned by the una<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nimous voice of Nations, by the Grace and Judicious Cenſure of Councils, by the Glory and Majeſty of Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racles; ſo that not to yield to her Prerogative, is an infallible Mark of an extreme Impiety, or a prodigious Arrogancy.</q>
               </p>
               <p>Let us return to <hi>Auguſtin.</hi> Grace hath gained a half Victory, the Battel is renewed hotter and more ſtubborn than before; he is convinced, but not converted; his Underſtanding yields, but his Heart revolts; that poor Heart was driven by contrary Winds: known Truth preſs'd him to profeſs it, his affection to ſome darling Sins, and to a fancied Reputation, held him back. <q>He deferred <note place="margin">1. 7. Conf. c. 11.</note> (as he owns) from day to day to live to God, whil'ſt without delay he died to himſelf. My Savior, (ſays he <note place="margin">1. 8. Conf. c. 11. &amp; cap. 5.</note> again) that is, the true way, pleaſed me, but it was narrow, and I had not ſtrength enough to break into it.—I ſighed after Liberty, but my Chains fell not off; thoſe Iron Chains which my own will had made, and ſhackl'd me in, by which my Enemy held me faſt.—My ſinful Affections, weak in their beginnings, had been heightned into Paſſion; Paſſion yielded unto, was grown a Cuſtom, Cuſtom unreſiſted, was become an uncon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>querable Neceſſity.—Two Wills, a newly-created one, the Off-ſpring of Grace, and my old ſenſual ſinful one,
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:98331:12"/> ſtrove the one againſt the other, and rent cruelly my martyr'd Soul.—I now ſuffered with pain what I had wrought in my ſelf with delight, and my ſinful Will uncontrouled had led me further than I would, before, I coloured my backwardneſs in ſacrificing my Vanities and Human concerns to thoſe of Religion, with this excuſe, that I waited but for a fair unqueſtionable diſcovery of the Truth; and now that I had it in my ſight, I found my ſelf chained up, and even afraid that my Chains and Excuſes ſhould fall off together.—My half-reſolutions of riſing and following you, my Lord, were like thoſe of one half aſleep: No one would be content to ſleep always, all judge 'tis better to be awake, and up; yet a drowzy head is loth to ſhake off a pleaſant fit of ſleep <note place="margin">Verba <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>enta &amp; ſomnolenta, modo ecce modo, ſine paululum, ſed mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>do &amp; modo non habebat modum, &amp; illud paululum ibat in longum.</note> when the hour of riſing calls: So it was with me; I was convinced it was fit and juſt that I ſhould yield to your Grace; my Judgment preſs'd me to it: but ſoft Plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures to be renounced, my Reputation to be blaſted by my Enemies, my Sincerity to be queſtioned by my Friends, enſlaved my Will. You clearly laid open before me that Truth which you invited me to avouch; it was too plain to be diſputed againſt: yet no anſwer could I return but thoſe dull and drowzy words, Shortly, yea preſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, leave me but a moment; but that <hi>preſently</hi> was ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver preſent, that <hi>ſhortly</hi> laſted long, that <hi>moment</hi> was eternal.</q> Behold the ſad Picture of a Soul that hath not yet loſt all pretence to eternal Bliſs, yet ſo dull'd by her ſins, ſo debauch'd by weak human fears, as to dare to ſtray from the way to it, againſt the loud and clamorous convictions of her own conſcience. A ſad caſe! and at that time that of <hi>Auguſtin.</hi> Great God! that Souls, created to poſſeſs an Everlaſting Bliſs, ſhould be baffled out of all claim to it, by ſuch poor, childiſh, weak fears! He was to <hi>change,</hi> forſooth! to alter his firſt Sentiment he had ſo often de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared to the World! He<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> that Learned Man, was to lay down his old Errors, <hi>to be catechiz'd,</hi> to learn (a little one in Chriſt) the firſt Elements of Religion, <hi>to take up a new Faith;</hi> what would the World ſay? how ſiniſtrouſly
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:98331:13"/> would they miſrepreſent his Motives? Weakneſs of men! <hi>who dare act againſt their conſcience, leſt the World ſhould think they do.</hi> 
                  <q>This miſery the Saint reflected on after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards, when he cried out, A curſe on thee, ſwelling <note place="margin">Confeſſ. l 1. c. 16.</note> River of human Reſpects! who ſhall bear up againſt thy Stream? who ſhall ford thee? what powerful Grace of God ſhall drain or dry thee up, and open me a paſſage?</q> God directed <hi>Auguſtin</hi> to a holy Biſhop, <hi>Sedulius,</hi> who had been a Spiritual Guide and Father to St. <hi>Ambroſe;</hi> by this Man's means God had deſigned to defeat this one great Difficulty at leaſt, which was ſo dreadful an Obſtacle to <hi>Auguſtin</hi>'s Converſion. His Exhortations had long been ineffectual, when God inſpired him to relate to <hi>Auguſtin</hi> the late Converſion of one <hi>Victorinus:</hi> You knew him at <hi>Rome,</hi> ſaid the holy Biſhop, you have often convers'd with <note place="margin">Confeſſ. l. 8.</note> him, and heard him both in the School and at the Bar; you know that for his eminent Parts and prodigious Rhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>toric, he was highly valued, ſo far beyond all others, that <hi>Rome</hi> had raiſed him a Statue in the moſt eminent place of the City, as to the God of Eloquence: He was the Darling of the Nobility, the Glory of the Senate, the Love of the People, and wanted towards Happineſs only (alas! the all indeed) true Religion. He was now far advanced in Age, when by reading all thoſe Books that were written by thoſe of the Catholic Church, God's Grace inſtructing him interiorly, he came to the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of the Truth. But he was Head of a contrary Party, or at leaſt the moſt conſidered in it. 'Twas hard to quit that ſweet Prae-eminence, <hi>and to have a new Intereſt to make.</hi> He would often tell me, not in public, but in private and familiar diſcourſe, That now he was converted, and of my Religion: I ever anſwered him, That he deceived him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, and that I ſhould never rank him amongſt thoſe of it, till I ſaw him in their Church, at their Prayers, at their Sacraments. He would reply, That God knew his heart; and what, ſaid he, do the Walls of a Church make one a Chriſtian? This was but a fond excuſe; alas he fear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to offend his Friends; to caſt a blur upon that
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:98331:13"/> fair Reputation with them which he had gained to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf. God pitied him at laſt; he apply'd himſelf to Read<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing again, and to fervent Prayer; he inſlamed his cold Deſires, reinforced his Reſolutions; and, fearing not to be acknowledged by Chriſt before his holy Angels, in caſe he bluſhed to confeſs him before Men; He (that great Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter of the Literate World!) abandoned his old Errors, which almoſt all the <hi>Roman</hi> Nobility and People were again infected with; and, tho' he knew that thoſe tall Cedars of <hi>Libanus</hi> would fall heavy on him, that his Friends would forſake him, his Admirers ridicule him, his beſt Supporters abandon him, he did not bluſh to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come a little one of Chriſt, <hi>aſhamed of his paſt Errors, not of the Truth he was to embrace;</hi> he ſuddenly, unexpectedly, declares to me, that he will go to a Catholic Church. With what joy did I lead him! Thither come, he refuſed to be privately admitted into our Communion; he made a public Profeſſion of his Faith, calling the whole Multitude for Witneſſes of the Mercy which God had ſhewed him. This Example thus related by the holy Biſhop, Oh how powerful was it! <q>I burnt, ſays <hi>Auguſtin,</hi> interiourly with a violent deſire ſuddenly to copy and follow it; I addreſs'd my ſelf to God in moſt fervent Prayers; Do, O Lord, ſaid I, do the ſame in my heart, awake and pull it back to you.</q> His Prayer was heard, human reſpects are totally laid aſide by him, nay he is convinced that nothing but Error, or Weakneſs in not daring to diſavow and to correct it, ought to be bluſhed at. One great point more God's Grace hath gained; now we are come to the laſt. No wonder if the Enemy, intrenched in his laſt Fort, makes the moſt vigorous, becauſe 'tis the laſt, reſiſtance.</p>
               <p>From the beginning of his Youth <hi>Auguſtin</hi> had found ſtrange Charms (as he acknowledges himſelf) in Virtue, eſpecially in that of Temperance and Chaſtity; but cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupted Nature found ſtronger, and more tempting ones, <note place="margin">Da mihi cont<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nentiam &amp; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatem<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> ſed <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> modo. Conf. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. 8. c. 7.</note> in Vice. His Prayer was then, Lord, give me Temperance, Continency, Chaſtity, <hi>but not too ſoon.</hi> In this diſpoſition had he continued till his Thirty-third year, convinced of
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:98331:14"/> his Duty, but unwilling to comply yet with it. Catholic Religion he liked well of; but with It the Croſs of Chriſt was to be embraced, Abſtinences, Penitential Works, Confeſſion, Reſtitution, and Self-denial, Purity of Heart and Body, a removal of all dangerous occaſions of ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning. <q>Oh (ſaith he) the Beauty of thy Law was to me greatly attractive! but I ſunk back with grief under my own weight, the violence of old ſenſual Cuſtoms.</q> Oh of how many is this the caſe, when called by God to <note place="margin">Qui intelligit De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um, &amp; non ac<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit ad Fidem ejus, ne vivat Chriſtia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus, ſed in ſi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e vult Pidem acci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pere ut mor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>atur Chriſtianus, qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem ſperat Deum cui cum mil<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>tare <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>rubuerit vult ab co ſtipendium ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipere. Q. Q. ve<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. &amp; nov. Q 126.</note> the true Church; or, if in it already, to Chriſtian Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues! But a ſad one! <q>For, as <hi>Auguſtin</hi> himſelf obſerved af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwards, Thoſe who being ſufficiently convinced when true Faith is taught, yet refuſe to ſubmit to it; <hi>reſolved not to live, yet hoping to die in it,</hi> can have but one of theſe two Motives of their delay; either a greater liberty of ſinning, with leſs reſtraint, with a weaker remorſe, du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring Life; or the confuſion they apprehend to be put to by that change. <hi>But, alas! what a God do they conceive you to be, O Lord, who bluſh to ſerve you, yet dare expect from you a reward?</hi>
                  </q> The force of this Example had con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quer'd in <hi>Auguſtin</hi> the difficulty he met with from human reſpects; God uſes the ſame to cure his laſt and inmoſt Wound, Sinful Cuſtoms. <hi>Potinian,</hi> a Noble <hi>African,</hi> and Friend of his, who followed the Emperor's Court, ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders him a Viſit, and finding S. <hi>Paul</hi>'s Epiſtles opened in his Study, expreſs'd the joy he had to ſee him beſtow ſo well his beſt hours. Their converſation thus falling on a pious Subject, <hi>Potinian</hi> takes an occaſion to rehearſe the eminent Virtues practiſed, and the wonderful Miracles wrought, by S. <hi>Anthony,</hi> not long before deceaſed, and ſo famous thro' all the Eaſt, even whil'ſt living, that the Great <hi>Theodoſius</hi> had often begged the Protection of his Prayers for his Empire and Army, and granted that he owed to them the Proſperity of the one, and the Victories of the other. <hi>Auguſtin</hi> wondred at the Greatneſs of thoſe <note place="margin">Tam recenti me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moria, &amp; prope noſtris tempori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus teſtatiſſima mirabilia tua in fide recta &amp; Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholica Eccleſia.</note> Miracles of ſo freſh a date, of ſo unqueſtionable a Truth, <hi>wrought in the true Faith in the Catholic Church,</hi> and ſtood amazed he had never obſerved, or even known them be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore.
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:98331:14"/> A great Motive to unite himſelf with it, in that Communion for which ſhe had that Hand and Seal of God to ſhew. From this great Guide, and Father of ſolitary Eremits and devout Religious, the Diſcourſe paſs'd to his holy Followers, and the moſt flouriſhing Monaſteries, and Religious Cloyſters, which <hi>Auguſtin</hi> could not but acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge to be a peculiar Flock of Chriſt endued with ſingu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar Piety; their Number and eminent Piety were a ſecond Motive to embrace the Faith which they, ſuch eminent Conquerors of the World, and exact Followers of Chriſt, did profeſs. <hi>Potinian</hi> finding him much moved, adds Fuel to this well-kindled Fire, by a relation of what he had been a witneſs of when the Court was at <hi>Treves.</hi> I went, ſaid he, with three other Courtiers to view ſome neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boring Eremits Cells and Gardens; the Company was di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided, two entring a Cell, where dwelt ſome of thoſe <hi>Servants of God, poor in Spirit, to whom, by that claim, the Kingdom of Heaven belongs,</hi> found on the Table S. <hi>Antho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny</hi>'s Life; they opened and read it, and God repreſenting by his interior Grace, in a far more lively way than the dead Letter could, the Virtues of his Servant, the one of them, an Agent in Court, inſpired with a holy Love for Virtue, and aſhamed of his ſo different a Life; What drive our hopes at, ſays he? What ſlatters moſt our wiſhes? It is, that we may perhaps gain our Princes Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vor; 'tis but a <hi>perhaps;</hi> many dangers will way-lay us before we reach it, and then that height is ſlippery, and threatens a ſore bruiſe in the fall; whereas in this very moment I may, if I will, enter into a particular Friend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip and Intimacy with my God. Full of theſe thoughts, he recollects his diſcompoſed mind, opens the Book again, and his heart at the ſame time to the Divine Seed of God's Grace, which took root preſently, and the Fruit ſoon appeared: God altered interiourly the whole frame of his Soul, broke all his Chains, ſever'd him from the World: He ſighs, and reads, and ſighs again; he ballances, reſolves, riſes, and now God's Courtier: The ſtrife is at an end, ſays he, adien Court and World, none of my hopes are
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:98331:15"/> now lodged in thee, 'tis God only I will ſerve; 'tis reſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, and that at this hour, in this place; and adieu Friend alſo, unleſs you have taken the ſame reſolution. He had; both rich enough, by that general reſolution of ſacrificing all to God, begun to build happily that Noble Tower of Chriſtian Perfection. How ſurprized were we, when ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving but viewed ſome neighboring Gardens, we found them ſo altered in ſo ſhort a time! ſo fix'd in their new re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolutions! If we were not <hi>otherwiſe</hi> altered, having heard their Choice and their Motives, <hi>ſo far</hi> we were at leaſt, as to weep for our weakneſs and inſenſibility. We did con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gratulate <note place="margin">Nihilo mutati à priſtinis, fleve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>runt ſe tamen.</note> their happineſs, envy their condition, crave their Prayers, and brought home with us a heavy heart, too too unſeparably wedded to this World, whil'ſt thoſe dwelt in mind in Heaven, in Body in their narrow Cells. Whil'ſt <hi>Potinian</hi> related this paſſage, what a ſtorm was raiſed in <hi>Auguſtin</hi>'s breaſt! who compared his wavering delays, with the firm reſolutions; his deafneſs to God's Voice, with the quick obedience of theſe his Servants. In vain he caſt himſelf behind his own back, and turned away his eyes, God placed him ſtill in his own ſight, and unco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered the old Sores of his laſting Sins. Not bearing with theſe interior reproaches, as ſoon as <hi>Potinian</hi> had left him he betakes himſelf to a Garden to divert thoſe thoughts: His intimate Friend <hi>Alipius</hi> followed him; God's Graces purſue thither their Fugitive, and renew a brisk Attaque againſt that ſtrugling heart. There, is expoſed unto him, how certain he is now that 'tis God who calls and preſſes him to obey: He had nothing to anſwer, all his put-offs and excuſes failed him; a ſtubborn ſilence had ſucceeded, a <note place="margin">Remanſerat muta trepidatio &amp; qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſi mortem refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>midabat reſtringi à fluxu con<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>uetu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinis<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> quo tabe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ebat in mortem. <hi>Conf. l.</hi> 8. <hi>c.</hi> 8.</note> ſtrange fear ſeized him; he apprehended more than Death to diveſt himſelf of thoſe ill habits that poyſoned his Soul to Death. <q>In theſe violent Convulſions of his mind, he ſtarts back towards his Friend, and ſeizing him, What is this, <hi>Alipius?</hi> (ſays he.) What did we hear? Unlearned illiterate people riſe and ſeize on Heaven, and We with all our eminent Parts and Knowledge, for want of Courage, behold we wallow in the ſink of our
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:98331:15"/> ſins. Are we aſhamed then to follow ſuch Leaders? or ſhould we not rather bluſh that we do not, at leaſt fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low, now they have opened the way?</q> His troubled and wandring eyes, his diſcompoſed and dejected looks, his pale co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>tenance, and faltring voice, ſpoke the reſt of his mind. He was ſinking into a kind of wholſom diſtracted<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, (as he calls it;) He ſits down, diſpleaſed with him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf even to paſſion, to ſee that he could not perſuade him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf effectually to make his peace with his God, by a full ſubmiſſion to his preventing Graces; that all the powers of his Soul violently led him to it, whil'ſt his ſtubborn Will abandoned him, and withdrew; that he would, and could not reſolve; 'twas but a half-will that ſtrove againſt the other wounded half, ſtill pa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ting and withdrawing back. His diſordered Soul ſuffered ſtrangely in this ſtrife! He pluck'd the hair off his Head, knock'd furi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly his Forehead and Breaſt; with joyned hands he clipt his Knees; then ſaid, How eaſily all the parts of my Body obey my Soul! How they move at her Will, and my Soul cannot obey her own Commands! She would reſolve, ſhe asks with a more violent paſſion that reſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolution <note place="margin">Imperat animus ut velit animus nec alter eſt, n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>c facle tamen vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luntas non uti<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> plena imperat, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>deo non eſt qued imperat.</note> from her ſelf, yet cannot obtain it. 'Tis I my ſelf that <hi>would,</hi> and I my ſelf that <hi>will not.</hi> God's merciful Graces purſue him with quick remorſes, by a ſaving ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity and tender cruelty, preſs him with ſhame &amp; with fears, ſuggeſting to him, <hi>That now was the fatal moment of which Eternity depended, now his Chains were to be broken, whil'ſt they were ſlackened, or never, in caſe he let his Paſſions ſtreight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Plagella ingemi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nans timoris &amp; padotis ne <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>ſus<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> ceſſarem &amp; non abrumperetur <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>d ipſum exiguum &amp; te<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>e quod re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manſerat &amp; reva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſceret iterum &amp; me robuſtius alli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garet.</note> 
                  <hi>them again.</hi> He ſtrove, and ſaid to himſelf, Ay, now, be it now done; yet it was not done. Being now with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in one ſtep of Peace of Mind, Joy, and Security, by a fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Victory, he ſuffered in his Soul the moſt violent pangs; he fell not back, nor yet dared to advance. In this critical minute his ill Cuſtoms, thoſe old Acquain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tances, as he terms them, his paſt Vanities, ſinful Plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures, and now-expiring Liberty, faintly pulling him, as by the Sleeve, ſaid, And wilt thou quit us? From this moment, for ever? And canſt thou (think'ſt thou) live
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:98331:16"/> without us? Ever hereafter under a conſtraint, ever checking, ever denying thy ſelf? Grace, for a laſt ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply, offered to his thoughts the Example of ſo many Servants of God, even of the weaker Sex, of tender Years, who had ſacrificed and ſuffered more to purchaſe Eternal Bliſs. <q>Theſe and theſe could, ſaid he, and thou canſt <note place="margin">Quid in te ſtas &amp; non ſtas? projice te ſecurus in cum, non ſe ſubtrahet ut cadas, projice te in cum, exci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piet te, &amp; ſana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bit <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>e.</note> not. Did God prevent them by his Grace co-operating with them; and art thou the only One whom God will abandon, returning to him? Why doſt thou rely on thy own Strength, or fear thy own Weakneſs? Caſt, caſt thy ſelf into his Arms who calls thee; he will not draw back, and let thee fall. Caſt thy ſelf into his Boſom; he will receive thee there, and cure thee.</q> The Storm grew higher; two Showers of Tears followed, a ſign that it was nigh clearing up. He could not bear the preſence even of <hi>Alipius;</hi> alas, he could not brook his own! He runs under a Figtree, (with ſuch Leaves <hi>Adam</hi> covered his Nakedneſs!) <q>there proſtrate on the ground, bathed in his Tears, he ſobb'd and ſigh'd, then gave vent to his grief in theſe broken words: How long, my God, ſhall I be the Object of your Anger, the Butt of your Juſtice? When will the Ray of Mercy ſhine? How long ſhall I ſay <hi>to morrow, to morrow?</hi> Why not now? Why not at this inſtant an end to my ſinful life?</q> 
                  <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſtin,</hi> Jeſus ſees thee under that Figtree, as well as he did <hi>Nathaniel,</hi> before thou ſeeſt him: His Mercy it is ſounds there ſo deep thy Wound, only that the Cure may be perfect; that hereafter, fruitful in Pious Deeds, thou maiſt eſcape the Curſe that fell on the barren Fig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tree. The happy moment is come, written in the Book of God's Mercy from all Eternity. A Voice is heard, <hi>Take up and read, Take up and read:</hi> He obeys, finding S. <hi>Paul</hi>'s Epiſtles by him, he lights on the 13 <hi>Rom.</hi> 13. God guiding his hands and eyes there he reads, <hi>Not in Feaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings and Drunkenneſs, not in Chamberings and Lechery, not in Strife and Emulation; but put on our Lord Jeſus Chriſt, and pamper no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> the Fleſh, gratifying its Deſires.</hi>
                  <pb n="29" facs="tcp:98331:16"/> Theſe words he had read often, but now a Ray of Grace writ the ſenſe of them in his mind, and ſtamp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed them in his heart. In a moment a comfortable Light, breathing Security and Joy, ſpread it ſelf into his Soul: His Tears were wiped off, his Doubts reſolved, his Fears and his Anxiety vaniſhed; he roſe a SAINT in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flamed with the Love of God, begins his Apoſtolical Labors by inviting his Friend <hi>Alipius</hi> to a like zealous Converſion, who had been all the while a dumb Specta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor, and who to ſhew the Riches and Varieties of God's Graces ſitted to all Tempers, without reluctancy, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out ſtrife or difficulty, ſurrendred himſelf at the read<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing only of the Sentence following in S. <hi>Paul, Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive,</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Infi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>um in Fide aſſamite.</note> 
                  <hi>and take him along with you, who is weak in Faith.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I ſhould now open unto you, Chriſtian Brethren, the Riches of God's Mercies heaped on this Saint; ſhew you his great ſteps towards an eminent Virtue, and the fulneſs of the Reward that attended it, even here, by <note place="margin">Numquid hoc eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> intra in gaudi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um Domini tui<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
                     <hi>Con. l.</hi> 9.</note> that ſerenity of mind, thoſe interior Joys, which he often conceived to be of the ſame Nature with the Bliſs of Saints in Heaven, and ſhort of them only in Length. But my Glaſs is at the loweſt ebb, my time expired: I ſhall treſpaſs no longer on Your Sacred Majeſty's Royal Patience. I will end with a tranſient conſideration on the Fruit of this whole Diſcourſe, which hangs on theſe three Truths. <hi>Firſt,</hi> That we can do nothing without a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinual ſupply of God's Grace, and therefore ought with aſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duous Prayer to preſs upon God's Bounty for it. <hi>Secondly,</hi> That Divine Grace once granted enables us to do all things, and that it is never denied when duly asked; whence it follows, that we ought without the leaſt fear to undertake whatever God moves us unto. <hi>Thirdly,</hi> That Grace requires a ſpeedy and diligent co-operation, or is ſoon withdrawn; and conſequently, that nothing is ſo dangerous in the great concerns of our Eternal Salvation, as delays, on whatever account.</p>
               <pb n="30" facs="tcp:98331:17"/>
               <p> No certainly, nothing available to Virtues here, or Happineſs hereafter, can be had without the help of Grace. S. <hi>Auguſtin</hi> is a plain Inſtance for it: Twenty years continual endeavors, a ſtudious application of ſo many Eminent Parts, the Tears of a pious loving Mother, the endeavors of the ableſt Divines of <hi>Europe</hi> and <hi>Africa,</hi> could not help him to ſee an almoſt ſelf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>evident Truth, what way of Worſhip God hath ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed us to honor him by, and where thoſe means lie which his Mercy hath allowed us, to attain that Bliſs we are created for. This Truth being laid open, his Will paſſionately moving him to declare himſelf of the Catholic Church, he had not yet the ſtrength to raiſe it to a Reſolution. Oh how truly are <hi>all the Crowns of</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Qui coronat te in miſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ordia &amp; miſcrationibus. Pſal.</note> 
                  <hi>God's Saints the Works of his Mercy, and his Commi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeration on our Weakneſs!</hi> How truly are all the Merits we can boaſt of, God's meer Gifts! His own ſad expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rience did teach S. <hi>Auguſtin</hi> how to expreſs this Truth ſo fully, ſo admirably, in his Book of Widows. To will, <note place="margin">Coronat munera ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> ſaith he, is certainly our own Work, if it be true of any thing, it is certainly ſo of our Will, that 'tis ſuch becauſe we will; and yet what little influence have we over our own Wills, relating to good! It muſt be awa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kened and ſtirr'd, or it lies as in a Lethargy; when awake, it muſt be healed and ſtrengthened, or the leaſt difficulty and pain overcomes it; when applied, it muſt be encouraged, enlarged, ſupported, or it is ſo very nar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row, <note place="margin">Noſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>m eſt vel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>le, ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>d vol<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>nt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> ipſa &amp; admonetur ut ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>rgat, &amp; ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natur ut val<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>at, &amp; d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>atatur ut ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piat, &amp; imple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur, ut <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>abea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. <hi>De Vi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ui<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>.</hi>
                  </note> ſo feeble, that it ſinks after the firſt offers, under the leaſt weight; and even when we think our ſelves moſt reſolved, moſt forward, after even many endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vors, we find our hearts very empty of all Virtues, if God hath not himſelf mercifully placed them there. How long do ſome continue in Error and in Sin? A conſtant Object of Gods Hatred and Juſtice, on the very brim of Hell, unconcerned, and without any ſenſe of their dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger? Ah! Gods Grace hath not awakened yet their dull Conſcience, lull'd in the ſleep of Sin. How many others
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:98331:17"/> behold their own Miſery, and ſigh often for it, acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge themſelves equally criminal and miſerable, ſee themſelves ſinking deeper and deeper, yet never offer reſolutely to releaſe their Souls from, and avoid, thoſe partly incumbent, partly threatning miſeries. Alas! they have conſumed the Subſtance and Vigor of their Souls in Sin; thoſe many deep Wounds have impaired their Strength; God's Grace, which only can, hath not yet wrought the cure. How many, in fine, after their Sins are pardoned, and they ſet in a right way, ſtumble at the firſt difficulty, and advance no further; or with little ſenſe, ever full of good Wiſhes, and empty of Ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects? Their narrow and poorly-ſtock'd Hearts, can re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive but little, know leſs <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> to improve it, till God by his Grace enlar<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> and enrich them. Oh then let us ever pr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ever ceaſe, and may this Grace be all we ask! <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>et us ever ſeek, but this Grace only; having ever in our hearts and mouths that frequent Prayer of the Church, <hi>O God, be intent on my help! Lord, haſten to ſuccor me!</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But again, for our comfort, that help being obtained, with what ſecurity may we not attempt the greateſt things! with what eaſe may we not perform them<hi>!</hi> S. <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſtin</hi> in that happy moment of his Converſion wondred <note place="margin">De quo imoalto<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> ſecreto evocatum eſt in momento liberum a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>bi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>rium m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>um? l. 9. c. 1.</note> from what dark Den, in which it had been ſo long locked up from him, his Free-will was reſtored; ſuch unuſual ſtrength he found in himſelf<hi>!</hi> It proved a ſatisfaction, a comfort to him, to want thoſe Pleaſures without which he had believed he could not live. How unerringly, through the courſe of his following <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ife, did he practiſe thoſe Virtues whoſe Names had been unknown to him<hi>!</hi> 
                  <g ref="char:punc">▪</g>Tis with Truth you mind us, Great S. <hi>Paul,</hi> That <hi>'tis God works in us both to will and to do;</hi> ſo little toil and <note place="margin">Qui operatur in nobis, &amp; vell<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> &amp; perficere.</note> pain is found in the performance, when God's Grace works in us a ſteddy fix'd Reſolution: And can we give place to any Anguiſhes, Fears, Apprehenſions, when God offers his Grace by calling us to a true Faith, to a pious Life? His Infinite Mercy is then at hand to create
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:98331:18"/> in us a Will, his Omnipotency to joyn to it a facility in obeying him. Who hath found a Treaſure, forms generous Deſigns, dares undertake great things, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceives he ſhall eaſily remove any obſtacle, becauſe that he knows the force of Gold, which in a moment can ſupply all wants. God's Grace is his Treaſure; 'tis the Riches of his Bounty, ſaith S. <hi>Paul;</hi> in a moment it gives <note place="margin">Divitias bonitatis ejus.</note> Strength to the Weak, Knowledge to the Dull and Ignorant, Courage to the moſt Timerous. 'Tis true we can do nothing without God, but 'tis equally true that <note place="margin">Jo. 15. Omnia poſſum in co qui me com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortat. <hi>Phil.</hi> 4.</note> we can do all things in him that enables us all. We can deſpiſe the ſoft deluding Pleaſures of ſenſe, with the Virgins; blot out whatever ſtains of paſt ſins, by our Tears, with God's pen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nt Servants; practiſe with eaſe all Chriſtian Virtues, with the Con<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ſſors; undergo and conquer all ſorts of Sufferings for Juſtice, with the Martyrs. But then let us ever remember that Sentence of S. <hi>Auguſtin,</hi> God cannot work with us, but when we <note place="margin">Deus non eſſet co-operator n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſi <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> eſſes operator. <hi>Aug.</hi>
                  </note> work our ſelves. If Grace be God's hand ever ſtretched to help us, and work with us; if a Divine Light, able to diſperſe the greateſt Darkneſs; if a Heavenly Science, expoſed to no Error, infuſed in thoſe who admit of it; if it be an eaſie conqueſt of all Vices, and of what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever Oppoſition to Virtue when uſed; if it be that with the help whereof all good Saints came to be ſuch. Oh, Chriſtian Brother, what a Treaſure hath laid ſo long hidden in thy heart<hi>!</hi> and how uſeleſs yet<hi>!</hi> That Grace is the whole Fruit of the Croſs of Jeſus, thy plentiful effe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctual Redemption; to neglect it is as deep an Offence as to tread under foot the precious Blood of our Redeemer. Ah<hi>!</hi> dig up that Treaſure then, ſtir it up, uſe that Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent, or it will be taken away. How long God will per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit it to lie dormant in your hands I know not. He gives <note place="margin">Secundum men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuram do<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ationis Chriſti. <hi>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>h.</hi> 4.</note> it not laviſhly, but according to the meaſure of Chriſt's Gifts. How ſoon yours will be filled I know not. If now you hear your ſelf called, anſwer; if moved, follow; if commanded, obey. Some one Grace, I know, is the
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:98331:18"/> critical one to each mans Salvation; ſuch were thoſe <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>muel</hi> offered to <hi>Saul, Nathan</hi> to <hi>David;</hi> the former paſt by his, and was ſet aſide for ever, an abandoned Repro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bate; the latter obeyed his, and became according to God's heart. Whether this day by my voice God hath <note place="margin">Gratiam inven<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus in auxilio opportuno. <hi>Heb.</hi> 4. 16.</note> not preſented to ſome one here the critical Grace, the laſt loud call, I know not; but this I know, that whoever obeys not his, whoever reſolves it not from this moment, ventures his Salvation upon a <hi>perhaps,</hi> than which there cannot be a more certain Folly, ſcarce a more crying Sin. Uſe then all that meaſure which God hath offered you, and your Fidelity will be bleſt by ſuch an increaſe of it, as will poſſeſs you with a Heavenly Bliſs, which God in his Mercy grant us all without end.</p>
            </div>
            <closer>Ad majorem Dei Gloriam.</closer>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
